Finding aid to the Judith Daniels papers SSC.MS.00744
Sophia Smith Collection
Judith Daniels papers
1948-2017
Sophia Smith Collection
Daniels, Judith
SSC.MS.00744
18 linear feet (17 boxes)
Judith Daniels, Smith College Class of 1960, was a magazine editor and the founding editor-in-chief of SAVVY, the first glossy magazine aimed at upscale executive and professional women. The collection is comprised of correspondence, memos, reports, financial records, publications, and photographs documenting Daniels' professional life, particularly her work on SAVVY magazine. Also included are college notebooks and papers from her time at Smith,as well as materials from high school and her college application process.
Biographical Note
Judith Daniels, Smith College Class of 1960, was a magazine editor and the founding editor-in-chief of SAVVY, the first glossy magazine aimed at upscale executive and professional women.
Born in Cambridge, Massachusetts, Judith Glassman Daniels grew up in neighboring Brookline, the daughter of Eleanor Saxe Glassman, an educator, and Joel Glassman, a shoe designer. She graduated from Smith College in 1960, earning a bachelor's degree, cum laude, in English. Typical for the time, she then took secretarial courses at a Katherine Gibbs school before landing her first job in publishing as a secretary at Doubleday & Co. in New York City. By the time she left for Farrar, Strauss & Giroux in 1962, Daniels had worked her way up to editorial assistant. In 1964, she moved on to the Russell Sage Foundation, serving as their public information officer until 1966 when she took a freelance position as a reader for the Book-of-the-Month Club. In 1968, Clay Felker hired Daniels as senior editor for his newly created New York Magazine. She was promoted to managing editor in 1972 and became managing editor of the Village Voice in 1974.
By the mid-1970s the Women's Movement had challenged many existing constraints on women's lives but barriers remained, especially within the workplace. Professional advancement for women continued to be limited at best and there were few, like Clay Felker, who helped make it possible for women, such as Daniels and Gloria Steinem, to advance in journalism. In 1974, out of this frustration, the Women's Media Group in New York City, of which Daniels was a co-founder, was born. Daniels recognized that professional women had little directed at them in the way of print journalism, a void she sought to fill with the magazine SAVVY, which she started in the fall of 1976. Putting together a concept paper, a business plan, and a dummy issue in her dining room with money raised by selling her grandmother's wedding ring, she went on to raise $1.2 million dollars from a group of investors to launch SAVVY. Aimed at professional women, SAVVY addressed business trends, workplace dynamics, and even workplace fashion. It was a great success; according to the New York Times, by the end of the first year, circulation was over 200,000. In 1982 Daniels moved on to Time, Inc. as "roving senior editor" until 1985 and then became managing editor of Life magazine until 1987. Daniels remained a leader in journalism for women throughout her career, developing multiple protypes for mass magazines aimed at women readers, particularly at Glamour and Self. After working part-time as editor of Clay Felker's Battery Park News, she joined Conde Nast as a contributing editor at Glamour (1990-1995) and then as executive editor for Self (1996-1998). In 1996, Daniels also established her own business, Judith Daniels Consultancy, Inc., working on editorial projects for a large and significant clientele.
Daniels' first husband, Ronald Daniels, a NYC attorney, died of cancer in 1980. In 1984 she married Lee Webb. They retired to Maine in 2004 where she became active in the Maine Women's Policy Center, the Women's Lobby, and the Maine Humanities Council and served as chairwoman of Center for Maine Contemporary Art in Rockport. Daniels was also an active Smith alumna as a longtime member of the Board of Directors of the Alumnae Association. She died September 1, 2013.
Sources: New York Times New York Times obituary (September 5, 2013) Donor Lee Webb
Scope and Contents
The collection is comprised of correspondence, memos, reports, financial records, publications, and photographs documenting Daniels' professional life, particularly her work on SAVVY magazine, the first magazine aimed at upscale executive and professional women. Also included are college notebooks and papers from her time at Smith College, as well as materials from high school and her college application process.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Lee Webb in 2015, additional materials accessioned in 2018.
Women -- Periodicals; Women editors -- United States; Women editors -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Women in mass media -- United States -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Women in the professions -- United States -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Women publishers -- United States -- Biography -- Sources; Women's periodicals, American -- History -- Sources; Women's periodicals, American -- History -- 20th century; Work environment -- United States -- History -- 20th century -- Sources; Women's Media Group; Judith Daniels Consultancy, Inc.; Advertisements; Annual reports; Awards; Business records; clippings; Contracts; correspondence; Financial records; Fund raising; Galley proofs; Grant proposals; Legal documents; notebooks; Periodicals; Proposals; reports; Questionnaires; Speeches; Surveys; Yearbooks; Daniels, Judith; Webb, Lee; Webb, Lee
- Judith Daniels professional papers, 1960-2013
  - Ambassador (TWA in-flight magazine with a feature article on SAVVY), 1980 (Box 7)
  - Biographical materials and photographs, 1954-2013 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    The following description was provided by the donor:
    Most of the box evidences her academic career at Smith College (1957 to 1960.) A complete set of all of the notes that Judith took for every course (in Smith spiral notebooks) is included, as well as all materials distributed by professors, and exam questions. Also includes her exams with professor's comments and all the papers she wrote for courses with professors' comments. A complete collection for every course she took in her entire four years at Smith.
    It also includes agenda, participants, and Judith's notes for her talk at Smith as speaker at Smith College's conference: "Alumni Media Gathering" held March 24-25, 2005l
    Also included are some materials from earlier days at Brookline, Massachusetts High School 1954-1958 including her editorship of the The Murivian, the school yearbook.
    Also includes a file on Judith's life and volunteer work in Maine after she retired and left New York. (That file includes brief materials on her board membership on the Maine Humanities Council, her help to the Smith Quarterly, and her chairmanship of the Board of the Maine Center for Contemporary Art (2008 to 2013).
  - Consulting work, 1996-2002 (Box 11)
    Files on editorial projects Judith developed, managed, proposed, and ran for a range of people and organizations that wanted to launch or revitalize a magazine.
  - Correspondence with authors and editors while at Glamour, 1990-1995 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence with authors and editors while at Self, 1996-1998 (Box 9)
  - Getting it Gazette (Women journalists' coverage of the 1992 presidential campaign, especially the DNC) (Box 10)
  - National Magazine Awards and Magazine Publishers Association: correspondence, evaluations, and speeches, 1990s (Box 10)
  - Publications and mock ups, 1984-1992 (Box 14)
  - SAVVY: correspondence, 1977-1982 (Box 6)
  - SAVVY: correspondence, questionnaires, planning, and design work, 1976-1977 (Box 3)
  - SAVVY: expense reports and budgets, 1977-1980 (Box 6)
  - SAVVY: financial and legal documents, 1976-1979 (Box 4)
  - SAVVY: financial records, reader surveys, reports, advertising, and articles/PR re: Daniels and the launch of the magazine, 1976-1983 (Box 5)
  - SAVVY (unbound issues), 1977, 1980-1983, 1987 (Box 7)
  - SAVVY (duplicate issues), 1980-1983 (Box 13)
  - Self (bound issues), 1996-01-1998-06 (Box 12)
  - Time, Inc. development projects, 1980s (Box 7, Box 8, Box 9)
    Primarily files relating to concepts and proposals created by Daniels in her role as Project Director for Time-Life, Inc.'s Magazine Development Department.
  - Undergraduate course notebook, papers and exams, 1957-1960 (Box 1, Box 2)
  - Work-related correspondence, memos, reports, press passes, 1960s-1970s (Box 2)
    Primarily relating to her work as editor at New York Magazine and the Village Voice. Other material documents her role as a founder of the Women's Media Group in the 1970s, the Women's Forum, and Women in Communications, all of which offered support and networking to women wanting to get started in writing, editing or publishing.
  - Work-related photographs, 1960s-1970s (Box 3)
- Judith Daniels papers and rolodex, 1948-2017; 2018-S-0083; 3 linear feet (3 record cartons)
  Various personal papers from adolescence and professional papers post-Smith College. Includes professional rolodex and mock ups from SELF and GLAMOUR magazines.
  - "GLAMOUR Woman of the Year" program invitations, 2006-2007 (Box 15)
  - "Confirmation - Temple Israel" Travel papers and correspondence, 1954 (Box 15)
  - "Village Voice" mock ups, lists of articles, internal memorandums, 1965-1977 (Box 15)
  - "Note from Edith of Smith Bulletin", July 24, 2017 (Box 15)
  - "Sweet 16 Invitations", 1954-1955 (Box 15)
  - "Littell Dance School 52-55" recital programs, 1952-1955 (Box 15)
  - "College Acceptance (Smith not here)" correspondence with Mount Holyoke College, Oberlin College, and Vassar College, 1956 (Box 15)
  - "Runkle School Diploma 1952" (Box 15)
  - "Wacipi Pines Camp for Hirls 1948-1952" memoriabilia, paper dolls, name tags (Box 15)
  - "Kamp Kackle" camp diary, approximately 1948-1952 (Box 15)
  - "Brookline High School 1955-1956" school programs, prom booklet, 20th reunion materials, 1955-1976 (Box 15)
  - "Time, Inc. Women Magazine" article drafts, internal memos, 1982-1984 (Box 15)
  - "LIFE 1968-1991" article drafts, internal memos (Box 15)
  - "Judith Course at Columbia 1991" syllabus (Box 15)
  - "Women's Media Group WMG 1987-1991" (Box 15)
  - "Judith Speech on Demographics 1985" Presented at International Industrial Conference Time, Inc. Panel, September 18,1985 (Box 15)
  - "Judith Book Notes, 1978-1990" (Box 15)
  - "Village Voice 1974-75" journal drafts and internal memos, 1974-1975 (Box 15)
  - "GLAMOUR Contents 1990-1995 SELF 1996-199" content lists, 1990-1999 (Box 15)
  - "A Birthday Book" from Gloria Steinem 50th birthday celebration at Waldorf-Astoria Hotel, 1984-05-23T00:00:00+00:00 (Box 15)
  - "New West Magazine" articles, 1976 (Box 15)
  - "New York Magazine" internal memos, articles drafts, annual reports, handwritten notes, newspaper clippings, 1969-1975 (Box 15)
  - "Owen Edwards 72-73" correspondence, 1972-1973 (Box 15)
  - "Tom Wolfe - Richard Fleuden 1971" correspondence (Box 15)
  - "Village Voice / New York Magazine 68-78", 1968-1978 (Box 15)
  - "Sony StartUp Notes 76-78", 1976-1978 (Box 15)
  - "Papers/Documents - Fight with Murdoch for control of Village Voice and New York Mag" legal documents, 1975-1977 (Box 15)
  - "Background - Murdoch - Take on of New York Mag and Village Voice" articles reporting on Murdoch, 1970-1979 (Box 15)
  - SAVVY plate, approx. 1976-1982 (Box 15)
  - "Judith's 1960's appointment books", 1965-1969 (Box 15)
  - "Judith's 1970's appointment books", 1970-1979 (Box 16)
  - "Judith's 2000's appointment books", 2001-2005 (Box 16)
  - "The Daily Life of Trend-Chasing Americans" Presented at International Industrial Conference Time, Inc. Panel, September 18, 1985 (Box 16)
  - Book reviews notebook, 2005-2006 (Box 16)
  - Book reviews notebook, approx. 2002 (Box 16)
  - "Smith College Art History Cards From Judith Daniels Class of 60" art poster cards, approx. 1960 (Box 16)
  - ERAmerica recognition award to Daniels and SAVVY, September 18, 1985 (Box 17)
  - Smith Alumnae Quarterly Spring 2004 cover featuring Daniels (Box 17)
  - 1987 National Magazine Award for Reporting, April 22, 1987 (Box 17)
  - 1981 Matrix Award Women in Communications, Inc (Box 17)
  - 1994 Clarion Award Women in Communications (Box 17)
  - Rolodex with note from Lee Webb, approx. 1970s-1990s (Box 17)